Guide to the John A.S. Adams Papers, 1951-1989 MS 048
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
John A.S. Adams geology papers
1951-1989
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Adams, John A. S. (John Allan Stewart), 1926-
MS 048
7 Linear Feet (14 boxes)
This collection contains papers from Adams' professional career as a renowned geologist and professor at Rice University. Included are papers regarding his careers in consulting, teaching, recycling and writing; also included is Adams' correspondence, membership in organizations and attendance at meetings.
Biographical Sketch
John Allan Stewart Adams is considered to be one of the founding fathers of the Department of Geology at Rice University. Adams attended the University of Chicago where he obtained four degrees (B.S., M.S., Ph. B., and Ph.D.) from the Department of Geology and he also received a Fulbright grant to study in Norway for two years. While at the University of Chicago, he was a two time All-American cross-country runner. Adams joined the Rice faculty as an associate professor of Geology and then became Chairman of the Department, served as a professor for thirty-four years, and was very popular with faculty and students. Adams produced numerous publications and garnered many awards and honors. He also served as: Principal Investigator on Lunar Samples, President of the Houston Philosophical Society, American Executive Editor of Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta, Councilman of the Geochemical Society, and consultant to Shell Development Company.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains papers related to Adams's careers in consulting, teaching recycling and writing. Also included is correspondence, membership in organizations and attendance at meetings.
Restrictions on Access
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated to Fondren by John A.S. Adams and JoAnne Adams (his daughter) and received on July 24, 1992.
Index Terms
Subjects
Geology; Universities and colleges
Document Types
letters (correspondence); syllabi; reports; minutes (administrative records); notes; articles
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University. Department of Geology and Geophysics
- Series I: Consulting, 1951-1989, 43512
  - Humble Consulting, 1958-1971; 43543 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Humble Consulting, 1972-1978; 43542 (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
  - Maine Nuclear Referendum Correspondence, 43541 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Subseries A: VHS videotapes, 43528 (Box 2, Folder -)
    - VHS Video Tapes: MNRC "The Loading" and "Out of State" 21 Sept 1987, 43540
    - VHS Video Tapes: MNRC/AdsTitcomb Fishing, 43539
    - VHS Video Tapes: Nova Co2 Greenhouse 1988, 43538
    - VHS Video Tapes: HL and P and STPP, 43537
    - VHS Video Tapes: Yes, Minister Whiskey Priest, 43536
    - VHS Video Tapes: MNRC "Father and Son" Al Giordano 14 Oct 1987, 43535
    - VHS Video Tapes: NOVA Greenhouse 1989, 43534
    - VHS Video Tapes: Unidentified tape, 43533
    - Compact Video Cassettes: Maine #1, 43532
    - Compact Video Cassettes: Maine #2, 43531
    - Compact Video Cassettes: 6 April 1988 FAC Meeting, 43530
    - Cassette Tape: Buck and Bob - Maine Tape, 43529
  - Uranium Resources Inc. – Comanche Peak (1 of 2), 1973-1982; 43527 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Uranium Resources Inc. – Comanche Peak (2 of 2), 1973-1982; 43526 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Comanche Peak Survey 2, June 6-7, 1973; 43525 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Atomic Energy Commission (AEC) – New York Office – Health and Safety, 43524 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Non-Humble Consulting (1 of 3), 1965-1977; 43523 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Non-Humble Consulting (2 of 3), 1965-1977; 43522 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Non-Humble Consulting (3 of 3), 1965-1977; 43521 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Allen's Creek Radon-222 Monitoring Proposal 1973-75, 1973-1975; 43520 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - HL and P Survey. Austin County, TX, Dec. 2, 1972; 43519 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - HL and P South Texas, 43518 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Consulting, 1954-1964; 43517 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Utility Data Corporation – NURAD, 1970-1974; 43516 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Shell Consulting, 1951-1958; 43515 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Consulting, 1983-1986; 43514 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Asbestos Fibre Study – Expert Witness, 43513 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series II: Correspondence, 43448
  - Hadi Ageli, 43511 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - A.C.S. Aguiar, 43510 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - K. Assaf, 43509 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Tom F.W. Barth, 43508 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Mohammed Baegi, 43507 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - P.M.C. Barretto, 43506 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Candyce Beck, 43505 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Alan Christopher, 43504 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - C, 43503 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Jeremy Dahl, 43502 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - D, 43501 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Farrington Daniels, 43500 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - E, 43499 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - George Edwards, 43498 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Roberto Fainstein, 43497 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Friesen, 43496 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Laura M. Gammill, 43495 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Gasparini, 43494 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - David Christian Gerlach, 43493 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Ghosh, 43492 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Alan Gregory, 43491 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - H, 43490 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Sam Harrill, 43489 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Hat, 43488 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Knut Heier, 43487 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Daniel Hicken, 43486 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Myron Horn, 43485 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Igor, 43484 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - I, 43483 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Ingerson, Dr. Earl, 43482 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - J, 43481 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Joel Kronefeld, 43480 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Kriti, 43479 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Kroner, 43478 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - K, 43477 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - A.A. Levinson, 43476 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Leif Lovborg, 43475 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Wayne M. Lowder, 43474 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - L, 43473 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - M (1 of 2), 43472 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - M (2 of 2), 43471 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - William Matthews, 43470 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - John Edward Oddo, 43469 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Odin, 43468 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - J. Kenneth Osmond, 43467 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Enio Pereira, 43466 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Howard M. Prichard, 43465 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - P, 43464 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Kalervo Rankama, 43463 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Alexander B. Ronov, 43462 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - R, 43461 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Jeremy R.D. Setter, 43460 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Alan R. Smith, 43459 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Schlaeffer, Carmen, 43458 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - S, 43457 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - T, 43456 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - David Todd, 43455 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - V, 43454 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - W, 43453 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Chi-Sheng Wei, 43452 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Dr. J.H. Whitaker, MCD, 43451 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Alvin M. Weinberg, 43450 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Z, 43449 (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Series III: Meetings and Organizations, 1970s, 43437
  - China – Seminars on Radioactive Resources Exploration, 43447 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Resources for the Future, 43446 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - International Atomic Energy Agency Panel. Vienna (1 of 2), March 5-10, 1973; 43445 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - International Atomic Energy Agency Panel. Vienna (2 of 2), March 5-10, 1973; 43444 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR) Workshop, June 20-24, 1977; 43443 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Geochemical Congress – Moscow, July 20-25, 1971; 43442 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Monaco Meeting, 43441 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Kansas Remote Sensing Conference, 1975; 43440 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Short Course on Uranium Prospecting – South Africa, Aug. 1976; 43439 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Geochemical Society, 43438 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Series IV: Teaching, 1977-1987, 43400
  - Courses – Miscellaneous, 43436 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Geology 322b – Mineral Resources, Spring 1978; 43435 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Geology 322b – Mineral Resources, Spring 1979; 43434 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Geology 322b – Mineral Resources, Spring 1980; 43433 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Geology 322b – Mineral Resources, Spring 1981; 43432 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Geology 321a – Environmental, Fall 1977; 43431 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Geology 321a – Environmental, Fall 1978; 43430 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Geology 321a – Environmental, Fall 1979; 43429 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Geology 321a – Environmental, Fall 1980; 43428 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Geology 321a – Environmental, Fall 1981; 43427 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Geology 321a – Environmental, Fall 1982; 43426 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Geology 321a – Environmental, Fall 1983; 43425 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Geology 321a – Environmental, Fall 1984; 43424 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Geology 321a – Environmental, Fall 1985; 43423 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Geology 321a – Environmental, Fall 1986; 43422 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Geology 321a – Environmental, Fall 1987; 43421 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Geology 322b, Spring 1982; 43420 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Geology 322b, Spring 1983; 43419 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Geology 322b, Spring 1984; 43418 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Geology 322b, Spring 1986; 43417 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Geology 455, 456, 43416 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Geology 321a, 43415 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Geology 200 Modernized, 43414 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Geology 556b, 43413 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Geology 322b – Economic Geology, Spring 1977; 43412 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Geology 322b, Spring 1985; 43411 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Geology 322b, Spring 1987; 43410 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Student Labs (1 of 2), 1962-1986; 43409 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Student Labs (2 of 2), 1962-1986; 43408 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Student Papers (1 of 2), 1962-1983; 43407 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Student Papers (2 of 2), 1962-1983; 43406 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Barium, 43405 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Student Papers, 1971-1979; 43404 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Student Papers, 1980 -1982; 43403 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Student Papers, 1983 -1984; 43402 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Student Papers, 1986 – 1987; 43401 (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Series V: Publications, 1954-1986, 43375
  - 4.4α (1 of 2), 43399 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - 4.4α (2 of 2), 43398 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Uranium Research/Speeches, 1954, 1983; 43397 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - "Geologic Reexamination of the Threshold Hypothesis", 43396 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Harper and Row, 1966-1969; 43395 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Gamma Ray Spectrometry of Rocks, 43394 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Articles by J.A.S. Adams, 1954-1965; 43393 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Articles by J.A.S. Adams, 1966-1969; 43392 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Articles by J.A.S. Adams, 1970-1979; 43391 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Articles by J.A.S. Adams, 1980-1986; 43390 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Articles by J.A.S. Adams, n.d.; 43389 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Articles by J.A.S. Adams: drafts, 43388 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - "Geochemistry of the Alkies", 43387 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - AAPG Paper with Weaver: "Geochemical Facies", 43386 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Obsidians, 43385 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - "The uranium geochemistry of Lasser Volcanic National Park, California", 1955; 43384 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - SCIENCE (magazine) AAAS, 43383 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Various articles, 43382 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - "Radon-222 emanation from zircons and stochastic considerations of discordant lead isotopic ages", 43381 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Thesis – 1951. "Some experiments with the diffusion of cations through geologically significant solids, 43380 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - National Radiation Environment (Book) (1 of 2), 43379 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - National Radiation Environment (Book) (2 of 2), 43378 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Papers by J.A.S. Adams rejected for publication, 1967, 1984; 43377 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - R.O.T.C., 43376 (Box 13, Folder 10)
- Series VI: Proposals, Grants and Contracts, 1962-1978, 43366
  - NSF Research Proposal Submitted, Jan. 1, 1978; 43374 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Shock Rock NASA Proposal, 1969; 43373 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Research Coporation, 1971-1973; 43372 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Lunar Radon – Rn222 Research (1 of 3), 43371 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Lunar Radon – Rn222 Research (2 of 3), 43370 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Lunar Radon – Rn222 Research (3 of 3), 43369 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Core research, correspondence, and proposal (1 of 2), 1962-1966; 43368 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Core research, correspondence, and proposal (2 of 2), 1962-1966; 43367 (Box 14, Folder 8)